Guide to the Brian Purnell Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History collection BCMS.0012
Brooklyn Collection
Brian Purnell Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History Collection
1987-2006
Brooklyn Collection
Purnell, Brian J., Ph.D.
BCMS.0012
1.8 Linear Feet 4 Boxes
Historical Note
The Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History Collection serves as a companion to the Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection. In the course of his research for his dissertation at New York University, Dr. Brian Purnell interviewed several activists who were members of the Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality(CORE). This collection also includes earlier interviews by other researchers that were obtained by Purnell for his study. During the early 1960s, the Brooklyn Chapter of CORE was one of the most dynamic civil rights organizations in New York City. From 1960-64, members of Brooklyn CORE led local demonstrations to desegregate apartments, integrate public schools, create jobs, and improve sanitation services to Bedford-Stuyvesant.
CORE members were also active in other civil rights organizations, including Freedom Organizations Coordinated for Unity in Shorefront (FOCUS), which protested housing discrimination in the Sheepshead Bay-Shorefront area, and Black News, a newsletter focusing on local and international issues in civil rights. Sonny Carson, who was an executive director of Brooklyn CORE and is interviewed by Purnell, published an autobiography in 1972, The Education of Sonny Carson, which was made into a film in 1974.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 34 interviews of 32 former CORE members, recorded between 1987 and 2005. Most, but not all, of these interviews are in both their original cassette format and in a transcribed copy. Notes, ephemera, and newspaper clippings accompany the transcriptions. Two compact discs and six floppy disks contain photographs of events at which Purnell presented his research, with many of his interviewees, in 2006.
Access
The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
Brian Purnell Civil Rights in Brooklyn Oral History Collection was donated to the Brooklyn Public Library by Brian Purnell in 2009.
Related Materials
August Meier and Elliott Rudwick. CORE: a study in the civil rights movement, 1942-1968. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1975.
Black News Table of Contents. A listing of articles in each issue of Black News, by date. Black News is a sub-series of the Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection.
Brian Purnell. A movement grows in Brooklyn: the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and the northern civil rights movement during the early 1960's. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI 2006.
Rioghan Kirchner Civil Rights in Brooklyn Collection
Clarence Taylor. Knocking at our own door: Milton A. Galamison and the struggle to integrate New York City schools. New York: Columbia University Press, 1997.
Jeanne Theoharis and Komozi Woodard. Groundwork: local black freedom movements in America. New York: New York University, 2005.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged alphabetically by interviewee name. Audio versions are on numbered cassettes, and printed transcripts, correspondence, and notes for each are in folders. Not all of the interviews are transcribed, and, conversely, some interviews are email-based, with no accompanying audio. Event photographs are organized by format.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Original cassette tapes are not available for research use. Access to the interviews is only available onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The compact disks and floppy disks in this collection are not open for research. The digital files on them are currently inaccessible.
Civil rights movements -- United States -- 20th century; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Akula, John. Interview transcript, April 25, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Banks, Gilbert. Interview transcript, photographs, April 1, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bibuld, Douglass. Interview transcript, consent form, notes, May 31, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bibuld, Jerome. Interview transcript, notes, pamphlet, January 2, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bibuld McField, Elaine. Interview transcript, notes, memorial pamphlet, February 18, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brezenoff, Stanley. Consent form, notes, correspondence, press release, July 1, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Carson, Sonny., November 12, 1995, November 13, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Craig, Maxine. Interview transcript, consent form, June 2, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Diamond, Edith. Interview transcript, consent form, July 20, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Flascher, Kurt. Notes from interview, May 23, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Fredericks, Maurice and Winnie. Interview transcript, May 9, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Goldwag, Arnold. Interview transcript, correspondence, clippings, October 13, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Group interview: Mary Ellen Phifer Kirton, Elaine Bibuld, Msemaji Weusi, Nandi Weusi, and Rioghan Kirchne, April 7, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Heinegg, Paul and Rita. Interview transcript, consent forms, notes, correspondence, clipping, January 5, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ipiotis, Shelley. Interview transcript, correspondence, March 24, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Kirchner, Rioghan. Interview transcript, consent form, September 29, 2000, October 21, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Kirton, Mary Ellen Phifer. Interview transcript, consent form, February 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Law, Bob. Interview transcript, consent forms, notes, correspondence, clipping, April 14, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Leeds, Oliver. Interview transcript, December 15, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Leeds, Oliver and Marjorie. Interview transcript, clippings, obituaries of Oliver Leeds, August 11, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Lewinson, Edwin. Interview transcript, consent form, November 20, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Miller, Ed. Interview transcript, March 3, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Owens, Congressman Major. Interview transcript, notes, correspondence, clippings, consent form, program, December 12, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Phipps Crayton, Francis. Interview transcripts, notes, consent form, November 20, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Rich, Marvin. Consent form, March 22, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Salvatore, Nick. Consent form, notes, correspondence, January 6, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Spiro, Phyllis and Rioghan Kirchner. Consent forms, notes, July 16, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Stein, Eleanor. Interview transcript, consent form, correspondence, notes, March 23, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Weusi, Msemaji and Nandi. Interview transcript, March 9, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Young, Jacqueline Lee. Interview transcript, notes, consent form, obituaries of Vincent Young and Oliver Leeds, December 3, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Banks, Gilbert, April 1, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 1)
- Group Interview, April 7, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 2)
- Kirchner, Rioghan, September 29, 2000, October 21, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 3)
- Kirchner, Rioghan, October 21, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 4)
- Goldwag, Arnold, October 13, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 5)
- Carson, Sonny, November 13, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 6)
- Bibuld, Elaine, February 18, 2001 (Box 2, Cassette 7)
- Weusi, Msemaji and Nandi, March 9, 2001 (Box 2, Cassette 8)
- Bibuld, Jerome, January 2, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 9)
- Bibuld, Jerome, January 2, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 10)
- Kirton, Mary Ellen Phifer, February 23, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 11)
- Kirton, Mary Ellen Phifer, February 23, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 12)
- Lewinson, Edwin/Crayton, Frances Phipps, November 20, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 13)
- Phipps Crayton, Frances, November 20, 2003 (Box 2, Cassette 14)
- Young, Jacqueline Lee, December 3, 2003 (Box 3, Cassette 15)
- Heinegg, Paul and Rita, January 5, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 16)
- Law, Bob, April 14, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 17)
- Craig, Maxine, June 2, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 18)
- Craig, Maxine, June 2, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 19)
- Diamond, Edith, July 20, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 20)
- Bibuld, Douglass, May 31, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 21)
- Bibuld, Douglass, May 31, 2004 (Box 3, Cassette 22)
- Galamison, Milton, October 21, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 23)
- Taylor, Gardner, August 1, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 24)
- Leeds, Oliver and Marjorie, August 11, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 25)
- Leeds, Oliver and Marjorie, August 11, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 26)
- Leeds, Oliver, December 15, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 27)
- Leeds, Oliver, December 15, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 28)
- Leeds, Oliver, December 15, 1988 (Box 4, Cassette 29)
- Leeds, Oliver, December 15, 1988 (Box 4, Cassette 30)
- Fredericks, Maurice, May 9, 1990 (Box 4, Cassette 31)
- Timmons, Gwendolyn, August 29, 1993 (Box 4, Cassette 32)
- Timmons, Gwendolyn, August 29, 1993 (Box 4, Cassette 33)
- Carson, Sonny, November 12, 1995 (Box 4, Cassette 34)
- Salvatore, Nick, January 6, 2003 (Box 4, Cassette 35)
- Salvatore, Nick, January 6, 2003 (Box 4, Cassette 36)
- Spiro, Phyllis and Rioghan Kirchner, July 16, 2003 (Box 4, Cassette 37)
- Owens, Congressman Major, December 12, 2003 (Box 4, Cassette 38)
- Brezenoff, Stanley, July 1, 2004 (Box 4, Cassette 39)
- Rich, Marvin, March 22, 2005 (Box 4, Cassette 40)
- Stein, Eleanor/Akula, John, March 23, 2005, April 25, 2005 (Box 4, Cassette 41)
- Law, Bob, March 29, 2005 (Box 4, Cassette 42)
- Brooklyn CORE Lecture at Brooklyn Public Library, February 2006 (Box 4, Disk 1-2)
- "I Remember Brooklyn: Civil Rights Movement 1960 - 1965" Images, February 2006 (Box 4, Disk 1-4)
- CORE Exhibit, January 2006 – March 2006 (Box 4, Disk 1-2)